Most people don't understand just how
old diamonds actually are. If this is
today and this is when the dinosaurs
went extinct, then this is when Pangea
split apart and the Atlantic Ocean
opened up. Then this is when the largest
diamond ever found formed, the famous
Cullinan diamond. It was split into
pieces and incorporated into the crown
jewels. But diamonds get way older.
Here's where our atmosphere first had
oxygen in it. And here's where the
famous Kimberly diamond formed. But they
get older. We know this because when a
diamond forms, tiny minerals are trapped
inside. And some of those have
radioactive that act like a natural
atomic clock. Over billions of years,
these elements decay into other elements
at measurable rates. So by calculating
the ratio between them, we can tell how
old they are. Here is where the oldest
diamonds ever found formed. That is
three quarters as old as the Earth
itself. But how they actually form is
crazier than most people think. So to
see that, subscribe.